<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>So Little Time</title>
    <description>This needs updating...
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 13:39:08 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 13:39:08 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title></title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;authors-conclusions&quot;&gt;Author’s Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MB’s interactions with MAO are the limiting factor in my personal use. The benefits (if real at all) are not sufficient to deprive myself of aged cheddar cheese. I will likely pick up this project again when the completed clinical trial has been published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plain-language-summary&quot;&gt;Plain Language Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MB may increase performance in many aspects of life including memory, attention, general physical performance, and possibly help prevent certain diseases like cognitive decline. MB has been used for more than a century and has a well known safety profile. Caution is advised for attempting to supplement with MB at home, however. Many over the counter forms may be contaminated with impurities that cause adverse health effects. The effects are radically different at varying doses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Herein contains the synopsis of my research on MB as a rarely used, experimental modifier of mitochondrial metabolism. MB can act as an alternative electron acceptor/donor enhancing the efficiency of energy production. MB tends to accumulate in areas of high metabolic need (e.g. brain tissue) due to MB’s aromatic and redox nature. [Phase 3 clinical trials] are under way using Rember© for treatment of Alzheimer’s Disease showing great promise. MB’s action is dose-dependent with many interactions that vary by concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purification and formulation of MB are paramount to ensure safety and efficacy. Impurities including heavy metals and similarly structured dyes are commonly found in commercial pharmaceutical formulations. The pharmacokinetics of MB depends highly on the structure of the dye and the absorption dynamics. MB can be bought OTC as dry powder or solution in lab, reagent, and sometimes illegal pharmaceutical grade and purified at home using easily obtainable chemicals and equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;physical-characteristics&quot;&gt;Physical Characteristics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moities&quot;&gt;Moities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acetyl-, Leuco-, Hydrates-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pharmacokinetics&quot;&gt;Pharmacokinetics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MB’s absorption is affected by pH, oxidation status,
MB has a substantially alterted pharmacokinetics from the more traditional zenobiotics due to the Mitochondrial Membrane Potential (&lt;abbr title=&quot;Mitochondrial Membrane Potential&quot;&gt;MMP&lt;/abbr&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interactions&quot;&gt;Interactions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given as the in-vitro EC50:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acetylcholinesterase inhibition (1 μM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nitric Oxide Synthase inhibition (5 μM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oxidation of Cysteine Residues (2-30 μM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;β-Amyloid Aggregation inhibition (2.3-12.4 μM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monoamine Oxidase B inhibition (5.5 μM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Glutamatergic inhibition (5-50 μM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Noradrenaline Uptake inhibition (50 μM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guanylate Cyclase inhibition (60 μM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monoamine Oxidase A inhibition (0.16 μM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhanced Mitochondrial β Oxidation (0.3 μM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adverse-interactions&quot;&gt;Adverse Interactions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently when MOAIs are mixed with tyramine containing foods, a hypertensive crisis can occur in certain sensitive individuals… Namely, me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methylene-blue-preparation&quot;&gt;Methylene Blue Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;purification&quot;&gt;Purification&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aiming for &amp;gt;98% purity. Minimizing heavy metal contamination and similarly structured dyes. Rubber gloves are your friend since MB dyes just about anything and at extremely low concentrations.
Each method of purification can be applied in any order or combination. As with any purification, more is better but at the cost of greater product loss. Most contamination will be in the form of inorganic metal salts and like structured dyes. Soluble impurities can be made soluble by the addition of a precipitant. Recrystallization allows separation of precipitated product from dissolved impurities. Organic extraction removes similar dyes. I am currently purifying a Methylene Blue product bought online labeled as 93% dye content. Procedures will be administered in this order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dissolve MB in excess water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add precipitant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Filter MB solution and discard filtrete&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organic Extraction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pH adjustment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heating to vaporize dissolved organic solvent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hot Salt Recrystallization&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(optional) Cool Acid Recrystallization for recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hot-salt-recrystallization&quot;&gt;Hot Salt Recrystallization&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20g crude MB dissolved in 1700 ml H~2~O at 65°C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 200g pure NaCl&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cool mixture to 22°C over 3.5 hours&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vacuum filter resulting crystals and dry at 75°C for 16 hours
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;optional washing with chilled, saturated salt solution&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cool-acid-recrystallization&quot;&gt;Cool Acid Recrystallization&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;20g crude MB dissolved in 1700 ml H2O at 65°C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cool to 22°C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adjust pH to 1 using aqueous HCl&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vacuum filter suspension and dry at 75°C over 16 hours
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;optional washing with chilled, HCl solution&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;organic-extraction&quot;&gt;Organic Extraction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 20% by volume immiscible organic solvent (DCM, Naptha, toluene) to MB solution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mix extensively for &amp;gt;10 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow layers to separate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remove organic solvent layer by draining or siphoning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeat 1-4 times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;metal-precipitation&quot;&gt;Metal Precipitation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4.5g crude MB dissolved in 125ml at 65°C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cool solution to room temperature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare a separate solution of sodium carbonate (163mg Na~2~CO~3~ in 10ml H~2~O)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add sodium carbonate solution to MB&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stir for &amp;gt;10 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vaccum filter and collect filtrate for further processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;final-procedure&quot;&gt;Final Procedure&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dissolve 5g crude MB in 230 ml H20&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heat solution to 65°C for &amp;gt;30 min while stirring&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cool solution to 10°C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare solution of 163mg sodium carbonate in 10ml H2O&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add Na2CO3 solution to MB solution at once&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stir continuously for 15 min&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vacuum filter and discard solid products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 50ml organic solvent (naphtha) to MB solution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stir vigorously for 10 min&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Siphon or separate aqueous layer from mixture ensuring no organic layer is taken&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discard or recycle organic layer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Repeat steps 8-11 twice more or as needed to yield colorless organic layer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adjust resulting solution to pH five using dilute HCl&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heat solution to 65°C for &amp;gt;10 min&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 118mg sodium chloride per milliliter solution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vacuum filter solution to yield purified crystals of MB&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dry crystals at 75°C over 16 hours to achieve final product&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Optional: repeat all or none of the purification procedures for greater purity or recovering product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;formulation&quot;&gt;Formulation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methylene Blue can be consumed as a solution through direct ingestion or formed into capsules. I began with the former for easy formulation and testing. This method leaves something to be desired for long term ease of use and definitely for taste. Depending on the oxidation state of MB, the taste can be somewhat off-putting and possibly cause some throat irritation. The reduced form is almost tasteless. The best option to mitigate these issues is to manufacture pills or capsules. Capsules are somewhat easier and completely mask the taste with little effort. Care must be taken to ensure MB is delivered in the stomach and in the reduced form as much as possible. Degradation of MB can occur in the high pH of the lower gut resulting in uneven and unpredictable effects. Again, quick-dissolving gelatin capsules are ideal delivery vehicles here. In addition, since only small amounts of MB are needed per dose, an inert filler should be added. Optional inclusion of a thixotropic suspending agent can increase optimal absorption by increasing the time for stomach passage. The addition of ascorbic acid will reduce MB in the low pH of the stomach to its more effective leuco form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further research is necessary to determine what effect the absorption and pharmacological effects of the alternate forms of MB would have on the results of previous trials and research. It may very well be the in vitro studies showing almost an order of magnitude increase in mitochondrial respiration with MB exposure are not translated well to humans simply because of the pharmacokinetic differences. Some research indicates that only leuco-MB crosses the BBB. Still, other evidence points to equal forms of color and colorless forms of MB in serum. Most likely this is caused by the balancing effects of other antioxidant compounds and electron donors in the blood stream. In any case, it can’t hurt to include an innocuous reducing compound in the formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dosing&quot;&gt;Dosing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clinical trials with Rember™ indicate good performance for patients with cognitive decline in the 30-100mg three time daily formulation. It is worth noting that the 100mg dose suffered from absorption issues and subsequently lost some of its efficacy. Many subjective reports from the community (/r/nootropics, longecity) indicate best performance at three orders of magnitude lower doses. I will summarily dismiss these reports as a combination of poor methodology, placebo, and the limitation of adverse hematological effects. The intended benefits are dose dependent so the formulation must reflect the goal of the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;liquid-formulation&quot;&gt;Liquid Formulation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maximum concentration of MB in water is approximately 43mg/ml (4.3%). The addition of ascorbic acid further reduces solubility. It is therefore best to aim for 1-2% concentration. If an accurate scale is available, daily preparation of solutions are possible. The scale that I am using at the moment has an accuracy of only 0.01g so I usually prepare large batch which can be portioned out as needed. As an example formula for a month’s supply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dissolve 5.4g MB in 270 ml H~2~0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add 10.8g ascorbic acid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stir for &amp;gt;10min&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consume 3ml three times daily&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solution is easily stored in 10ml syringes. Consumption can be done by directly squirting the solution to the back of the tongue. Although, this method results in a very blue tongue. An alternative is to dispense the solution into a larger amount of water to consume over several minutes. Of course, you could dispense an entire day’s worth of MB into a water bottle and sip throughout the day resulting in very even serum concentrations. I’m usually to busy/distracted to remember to do this method and end up with half drunk bottles at bedtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With those issues in mind I have chosen easily available products to create this formula. Microcrystalline cellulose will function as the filler and excipient. I was able to obtain a sample of Aerosil 200, a commercial colloidal silicon dioxide product intended as a thixotropic suspending agent. The ideal dose as indicated by the clinical trials of Rember will be between thirty and ninety milligrams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;unsorted&quot;&gt;Unsorted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cationic thiazine dye&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;low redox potential - efficient cycling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tyramine induced hypertensive crisis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;genotoxic effects with concurrent light exposure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;light exposure with MB alters function during in vitro experiments (photosensitized)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;major metabolites, azure B &amp;amp; A, and their effects on MAOs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- Abbreviations --&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 13:39:08 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/21/2015-06-08-methyleneblue.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/12/21/2015-06-08-methyleneblue.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Theory of Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;stm&quot;&gt;STM&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goal: To be able to reproduce all previous knowledge on a particular topic from memory - exact and conceptual replication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppositions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;older information is more likely to be false&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;older information is more likely understood and learned first&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information volume increases with time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encoding time is a limiting factor on learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;information volume is a limiting factor on learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;writing is the largest store of information
*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short cut suppositions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conceptual replication is more important than exact replication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start from the earliest, most influential papers. Contrast early beliefs and suppositions with current theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be helpful to others following this path to provide s&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/brain/2016/09/19/Theory-of-Learning.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/brain/2016/09/19/Theory-of-Learning.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>brain</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>AI</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/chemistry/2016/09/19/chemintro.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/chemistry/2016/09/19/chemintro.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>AI</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;ai-algorithms&quot;&gt;AI Algorithms&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Monte Carlo Tree Search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;key-terms&quot;&gt;Key Terms&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;art&quot;&gt;ART&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bottom-up activation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;top-down expectations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;category&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;competitive learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hebbian learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;anti-hebbian learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lateral inhibition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;attention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;intention/attention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;catastrophic forgetting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;modulatory on-center&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;modulatory off-surround&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;resonance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;attentional system
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;expected events&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;familiar events&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;resonance&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;attention&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;learning&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;recognition&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Temporal cortex - Prefrontal cortex&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;orienting system
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;unexpected events&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;unfamiliar events&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;reset&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;memory search&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hypothesis testing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;hippocampal system&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;event-related potentials&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;laminar computing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working memory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sequence learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bipole property&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;working memory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;primacy gradient
*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;numenta&quot;&gt;Numenta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SDR
*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/programming,brain/2016/09/19/AI.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/programming,brain/2016/09/19/AI.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>programming,brain</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>HTM on Parallella</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;specifications&quot;&gt;Specifications&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parallella board - kickstarter version with Zynq 7020
16-core Epiphany processor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;initial-setup&quot;&gt;Initial Setup&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo apt update&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo apt upgrade&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;static-ip-configuration&quot;&gt;Static IP Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo vi /etc/network/interfaces.d/eth0&lt;/code&gt;
Changed “dhcp” to static and added the relevant information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;auto eth0
iface eth0 inet static
        address 192.168.1.3
        netmask 255.255.255.0
        gateway 192.168.1.1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modified the DNS server configuration.
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo vi /etc/resolv.conf&lt;/code&gt;
Modified to include one original DNS server from my ISP (75.76.84.70), one google server, and my gateway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;domain knology.net
search knology.net
nameserver 75.76.84.70
nameserver 8.8.8.8
nameserver 192.168.1.1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;nodejs&quot;&gt;Node.js&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Node.js Source Code] https://nodejs.org/dist/v4.5.0/node-v4.5.0.tar.gz
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;wget https://nodejs.org/dist/v4.5.0/node-v4.5.0.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tar -xvf node-v4.5.0.tar.gz&lt;/code&gt;
`cd node-v4.5.0’
‘sudo ./configure’
‘sudo make -j16’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;apendix-a-installed-apps&quot;&gt;Apendix A: Installed Apps&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;acl&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adduser&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;apt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;apt-utils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at-spi2-core&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;avahi-daemon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;base-files&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;base-passwd&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bash&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bind9-host&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;binutils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bison&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bsdmainutils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bsdutils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build-essential&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;busybox-initramfs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bwm-ng&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bzip2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ca-certificates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clinfo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;colord&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;colord-data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;console-setup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;console-setup-linux&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;coreutils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cpio&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cpp&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cpp-4.9&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cron&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;curl&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dash&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dbus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dconf-gsettings-backend:armhf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dconf-service&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dctrl-tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;debconf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;debianutils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;device-tree-compiler&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;devscripts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dh-python&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;diffstat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;diffutils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;distro-info-data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dmsetup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;docbook-xml&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dpkg&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dpkg-dev&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dput&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;e2fslibs:armhf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;e2fsprogs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emacs-nox&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emacs24-bin-common&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emacs24-common&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emacs24-common-non-dfsg&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emacs24-nox&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emacsen-common&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ethtool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fake-hwclock&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fakeroot&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;findutils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flex&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fontconfig&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fontconfig-config&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fonts-dejavu-core&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ftp&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;g++&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;g++-4.9&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gawk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gcc&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gcc-4.9&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gcc-4.9-base:armhf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gcc-5-base:armhf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gdb&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gdbserver&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;geoip-database&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gettext&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gettext-base&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;git&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;git-man&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;glib-networking:armhf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;glib-networking-common&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;glib-networking-services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gnupg&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gpgv&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;grep&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;groff-base&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gsettings-desktop-schemas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gzip&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hardening-includes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hicolor-icon-theme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hostname&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;htop&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;i2c-tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ifplugd&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ifupdown&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;info&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;init&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;init-system-helpers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;initramfs-tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;initramfs-tools-bin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;initscripts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;insserv&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;install-info&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;intltool-debian&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iperf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iproute&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iproute2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iputils-ping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;isc-dhcp-client&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;isc-dhcp-common&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;iso-codes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;kbd&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;keyboard-configuration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;klibc-utils&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;kmod&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;krb5-locales&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;language-pack-en&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;language-pack-en-base&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;less&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;libacl1:armhf
libalgorithm-c3-perl
libalgorithm-diff-perl
libalgorithm-diff-xs-perl
libalgorithm-merge-perl
liballegro4.4:armhf
libapparmor1:armhf
libapt-inst1.5:armhf
libapt-pkg-perl
libapt-pkg4.12:armhf
libarchive-extract-perl
libarchive-zip-perl
libasan1:armhf
libasn1-8-heimdal:armhf
libasound2:armhf
libasound2-data
libasprintf-dev:armhf
libasprintf0c2:armhf
libasyncns0:armhf
libatk-bridge2.0-0:armhf
libatk1.0-0:armhf
libatk1.0-data
libatm1:armhf
libatomic1:armhf
libatspi2.0-0:armhf
libattr1:armhf
libaudit-common
libaudit1:armhf
libauthen-sasl-perl
libavahi-client3:armhf
libavahi-common-data:armhf
libavahi-common3:armhf
libavahi-core7:armhf
libbabeltrace-ctf1:armhf
libbabeltrace1:armhf
libbind9-90
libbison-dev:armhf
libblkid1:armhf
libboost-filesystem1.55.0:armhf
libboost-system1.55.0:armhf
libbsd0:armhf
libbz2-1.0:armhf
libc-bin
libc-dev-bin
libc6:armhf
libc6-dbg:armhf
libc6-dev:armhf
libcaca0:armhf
libcairo-gobject2:armhf
libcairo-perl
libcairo2:armhf
libcap-ng0:armhf
libcap2:armhf
libcap2-bin
libcgi-fast-perl
libcgi-pm-perl
libcgmanager0:armhf
libck-connector0:armhf
libclass-accessor-perl
libclass-c3-perl
libclass-c3-xs-perl
libclc-dev
libclone-perl
libcloog-isl4:armhf
libcolord2:armhf
libcolorhug2:armhf
libcomerr2:armhf
libcommon-sense-perl
libconfig++-dev:armhf
libconfig++9:armhf
libconfig-dev:armhf
libconfig-doc
libconfig9:armhf
libcpan-meta-perl
libcroco3:armhf
libcryptsetup4
libcups2:armhf
libcurl3:armhf
libcurl3-gnutls:armhf
libdaemon0:armhf
libdata-optlist-perl
libdata-section-perl
libdatrie1:armhf
libdb5.3:armhf
libdbus-1-3:armhf
libdconf1:armhf
libdebconfclient0:armhf
libdevil-dev
libdevil1c2
libdevmapper1.02.1:armhf
libdigest-hmac-perl
libdistro-info-perl
libdns-export100
libdns100
libdpkg-perl
libdrm-dev:armhf
libdrm-exynos1:armhf
libdrm-freedreno1:armhf
libdrm-nouveau2:armhf
libdrm-omap1:armhf
libdrm-radeon1:armhf
libdrm2:armhf
libedit2:armhf
libelf1:armhf
libelfg0:armhf
libelfg0-dev
libemail-valid-perl
libencode-locale-perl
libept1.4.12:armhf
liberror-perl
libestr0
libevent-2.0-5:armhf
libevent-core-2.0-5:armhf
libevent-dev
libevent-extra-2.0-5:armhf
libevent-openssl-2.0-5:armhf
libevent-pthreads-2.0-5:armhf
libexif12:armhf
libexpat1:armhf
libexporter-lite-perl
libfakeroot:armhf
libfcgi-perl
libffi6:armhf
libfftw3-3:armhf
libfftw3-bin
libfftw3-dev:armhf
libfftw3-double3:armhf
libfftw3-single3:armhf
libfile-basedir-perl
libfile-fcntllock-perl
libfile-listing-perl
libfl-dev:armhf
libflac8:armhf
libfont-afm-perl
libfontconfig1:armhf
libfreetype6:armhf
libfribidi0:armhf
libgcc-4.9-dev:armhf
libgcc1:armhf
libgcrypt20:armhf
libgd3:armhf
libgdbm3:armhf
libgdk-pixbuf2.0-0:armhf
libgdk-pixbuf2.0-common
libgeoip1:armhf
libgettextpo-dev:armhf
libgettextpo0:armhf
libgl1-mesa-dev:armhf
libgl1-mesa-dri:armhf
libgl1-mesa-glx:armhf
libglapi-mesa:armhf
libglib-perl
libglib2.0-0:armhf
libglib2.0-data
libglu1-mesa:armhf
libgmp-dev:armhf
libgmp10:armhf
libgmp3-dev
libgmpxx4ldbl:armhf
libgnutls-deb0-28:armhf
libgnutls-openssl27:armhf
libgomp1:armhf
libgpg-error0:armhf
libgphoto2-6:armhf
libgphoto2-l10n
libgphoto2-port10:armhf
libgpm2:armhf
libgraphite2-3:armhf
libgssapi-krb5-2:armhf
libgssapi3-heimdal:armhf
libgtk-3-0:armhf
libgtk-3-bin
libgtk-3-common
libgtk2-perl
libgtk2.0-0:armhf
libgtk2.0-bin
libgtk2.0-common
libgudev-1.0-0:armhf
libgusb2:armhf
libharfbuzz0b:armhf
libhcrypto4-heimdal:armhf
libheimbase1-heimdal:armhf
libheimntlm0-heimdal:armhf
libhogweed2:armhf
libhtml-form-perl
libhtml-format-perl
libhtml-parser-perl
libhtml-tagset-perl
libhtml-tree-perl
libhttp-cookies-perl
libhttp-daemon-perl
libhttp-date-perl
libhttp-message-perl
libhttp-negotiate-perl
libhx509-5-heimdal:armhf
libicu52:armhf
libidn11:armhf
libieee1284-3:armhf
libintl-perl
libio-html-perl
libio-pty-perl
libio-socket-inet6-perl
libio-socket-ssl-perl
libio-string-perl
libio-stringy-perl
libipc-run-perl
libirs-export91
libisc-export95
libisc95
libisccc90
libisccfg-export90
libisccfg90
libisl13:armhf
libjasper1:armhf
libjbig-dev:armhf
libjbig0:armhf
libjpeg-dev:armhf
libjpeg-turbo8:armhf
libjpeg-turbo8-dev:armhf
libjpeg8:armhf
libjpeg8-dev:armhf
libjs-jquery
libjson-c2:armhf
libjson-glib-1.0-0:armhf
libjson-glib-1.0-common
libjson-perl
libjson-xs-perl
libjson0:armhf
libk5crypto3:armhf
libkeyutils1:armhf
libklibc
libkmod2:armhf
libkrb5-26-heimdal:armhf
libkrb5-3:armhf
libkrb5support0:armhf
liblcms2-2:armhf
liblcms2-dev:armhf
libldap-2.4-2:armhf
liblist-moreutils-perl
libllvm3.6:armhf
liblocale-gettext-perl
liblockfile-bin
liblockfile1:armhf
liblog-message-perl
liblog-message-simple-perl
libltdl7:armhf
liblua5.2-0:armhf
liblwp-mediatypes-perl
liblwp-protocol-https-perl
liblwres90
liblzma-dev:armhf
liblzma5:armhf
libmagic1:armhf
libmailtools-perl
libmirclient8:armhf
libmircommon3:armhf
libmirprotobuf0:armhf
libmng2:armhf
libmodule-build-perl
libmodule-pluggable-perl
libmodule-signature-perl
libmount1:armhf
libmpc-dev:armhf
libmpc3:armhf
libmpdec2:armhf
libmpfr-dev:armhf
libmpfr4:armhf
libmro-compat-perl
libncurses5:armhf
libncursesw5:armhf
libnet-dns-perl
libnet-domain-tld-perl
libnet-http-perl
libnet-ip-perl
libnet-smtp-ssl-perl
libnet-ssleay-perl
libnettle4:armhf
libnewt0.52:armhf
libnih-dbus1:armhf
libnih1:armhf
libnss-mdns:armhf
libogg0:armhf
libopts25:armhf
libp11-kit0:armhf
libpackage-constants-perl
libpam-modules:armhf
libpam-modules-bin
libpam-runtime
libpam-systemd:armhf
libpam0g:armhf
libpango-1.0-0:armhf
libpango-perl
libpangocairo-1.0-0:armhf
libpangoft2-1.0-0:armhf
libparams-util-perl
libparse-debcontrol-perl
libparse-debianchangelog-perl
libpcre3:armhf
libperl5.20
libperlio-gzip-perl
libpipeline1:armhf
libpixman-1-0:armhf
libplymouth4:armhf
libpng12-0:armhf
libpod-latex-perl
libpod-readme-perl
libpolkit-agent-1-0:armhf
libpolkit-backend-1-0:armhf
libpolkit-gobject-1-0:armhf
libpopt0:armhf
libprocps3:armhf
libprotobuf9:armhf
libproxy1:armhf
libpthread-stubs0-dev:armhf
libpulse0:armhf
libpython-stdlib:armhf
libpython2.7:armhf
libpython2.7-minimal:armhf
libpython2.7-stdlib:armhf
libpython3-stdlib:armhf
libpython3.4:armhf
libpython3.4-minimal:armhf
libpython3.4-stdlib:armhf
librarian0
libreadline6:armhf
libregexp-common-perl
librest-0.7-0:armhf
libroken18-heimdal:armhf
librtmp1:armhf
libruby2.1:armhf
libsane:armhf
libsane-common
libsasl2-2:armhf
libsasl2-modules:armhf
libsasl2-modules-db:armhf
libsdl1.2debian:armhf
libselinux1:armhf
libsemanage-common
libsemanage1:armhf
libsensors4:armhf
libsepol1:armhf
libsigsegv2:armhf
libslang2:armhf
libsmartcols1:armhf
libsndfile1:armhf
libsocket6-perl
libsoftware-license-perl
libsoup-gnome2.4-1:armhf
libsoup2.4-1:armhf
libsqlite3-0:armhf
libss2:armhf
libssl1.0.0:armhf
libstatgrab9
libstdc++-4.9-dev:armhf
libstdc++6:armhf
libsub-exporter-perl
libsub-install-perl
libsub-name-perl
libsystemd0:armhf
libtasn1-6:armhf
libtcl8.6:armhf
libterm-ui-perl
libtext-levenshtein-perl
libtext-soundex-perl
libtext-template-perl
libtext-unidecode-perl
libthai-data
libthai0:armhf
libtie-ixhash-perl
libtiff5:armhf
libtiff5-dev:armhf
libtiffxx5:armhf
libtimedate-perl
libtinfo5:armhf
libtxc-dxtn-s2tc0:armhf
libubsan0:armhf
libudev1:armhf
libunistring0:armhf
liburi-perl
libusb-0.1-4:armhf
libusb-1.0-0:armhf
libustr-1.0-1:armhf
libuuid1:armhf
libv4l-0:armhf
libv4lconvert0:armhf
libvorbis0a:armhf
libvorbisenc2:armhf
libvpx1:armhf
libvte-2.90-9
libvte-2.90-common
libwayland-client0:armhf
libwayland-cursor0:armhf
libwind0-heimdal:armhf
libwrap0:armhf
libwww-perl
libwww-robotrules-perl
libx11-6:armhf
libx11-data
libx11-dev:armhf
libx11-doc
libx11-xcb-dev:armhf
libx11-xcb1:armhf
libxapian22
libxau-dev:armhf
libxau6:armhf
libxcb-dri2-0:armhf
libxcb-dri2-0-dev:armhf
libxcb-dri3-0:armhf
libxcb-dri3-dev:armhf
libxcb-glx0:armhf
libxcb-glx0-dev:armhf
libxcb-present-dev:armhf
libxcb-present0:armhf
libxcb-randr0:armhf
libxcb-randr0-dev:armhf
libxcb-render0:armhf
libxcb-render0-dev:armhf
libxcb-shape0:armhf
libxcb-shape0-dev:armhf
libxcb-shm0:armhf
libxcb-sync-dev:armhf
libxcb-sync1:armhf
libxcb-xfixes0:armhf
libxcb-xfixes0-dev:armhf
libxcb1:armhf
libxcb1-dev:armhf
libxcomposite1:armhf
libxcursor1:armhf
libxdamage-dev:armhf
libxdamage1:armhf
libxdmcp-dev:armhf
libxdmcp6:armhf
libxext-dev:armhf
libxext6:armhf
libxfixes-dev:armhf
libxfixes3:armhf
libxi6:armhf
libxinerama1:armhf
libxkbcommon0:armhf
libxml-libxml-perl
libxml-namespacesupport-perl
libxml-parser-perl
libxml-sax-base-perl
libxml-sax-expat-perl
libxml-sax-perl
libxml2:armhf
libxmuu1:armhf
libxpm4:armhf
libxrandr2:armhf
libxrender1:armhf
libxshmfence-dev:armhf
libxshmfence1:armhf
libxtables10
libxtst6:armhf
libxxf86dga1:armhf
libxxf86vm-dev:armhf
libxxf86vm1:armhf
libyaml-0-2:armhf
linaro-nano
linaro-overlay-minimal
lintian
linux-firmware
linux-libc-dev:armhf
lm-sensors
locales
lockfile-progs
login
logrotate
lsb-base
lsb-release
m4
make
makedev
man-db
manpages
manpages-dev
mawk
mesa-common-dev:armhf
mime-support
mir-client-platform-mesa2:armhf
module-init-tools
mount
mountall
multiarch-support
nano
ncurses-base
ncurses-bin
ncurses-term
net-tools
netbase
netcat-openbsd
ntp
ntpdate
ocl-icd-dev
ocl-icd-libopencl1:armhf
ocl-icd-opencl-dev:armhf
opencl-headers
openssh-client
openssh-server
openssh-sftp-server
openssl
passwd
patch
patchutils
perl
perl-base
perl-modules
pkg-config
plymouth
plymouth-theme-ubuntu-text
policykit-1
procps
python
python-apt-common
python-minimal
python2.7
python2.7-minimal
python3
python3-apt
python3-chardet
python3-debian
python3-magic
python3-minimal
python3-pkg-resources
python3-requests
python3-six
python3-urllib3
python3.4
python3.4-minimal
rarian-compat
read-edid
readline-common
rename
rsync
rsyslog
ruby
ruby2.1
rubygems-integration
screen
sed
sensible-utils
sgml-base
sgml-data
shared-mime-info
ssh
ssh-import-id
strace
sudo
synaptic
systemd
systemd-sysv
sysv-rc
sysvinit-utils
t1utils
tar
tcpd
tcsh
texinfo
tmux
tzdata
ubuntu-keyring
ucf
udev
unzip
upstart
usbutils
util-linux
vim-common
vim-nox
vim-runtime
wdiff
wget
whiptail
x11-common
x11proto-core-dev
x11proto-damage-dev
x11proto-dri2-dev
x11proto-fixes-dev
x11proto-gl-dev
x11proto-input-dev
x11proto-kb-dev
x11proto-xext-dev
x11proto-xf86vidmode-dev
xauth
xdg-user-dirs
xkb-data
xml-core
xorg-sgml-doctools
xtrans-dev
xz-utils
zlib1g:armhf
zlib1g-dev:armhf&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/programming/2016/09/14/parallella.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/programming/2016/09/14/parallella.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>programming</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>H2O2 Concentraion</title>
        <description>&lt;h3&gt;Concetration of Hydrogen Peroxide Soltuion via Evaporation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Motivation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hydrogen peroxide is used in many experiments as a source of oxygen. It is famous for the &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ezsur0L0L1c&quot;&gt;elephant toothpaste&lt;/a&gt; experiment. H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is also used for many explosive syntheses (which I won't be covering here). Unfortunately, it has become increasingly difficult to obtain 30% hydrogen peroxide. H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is sold in almost every grocery store as 3% stabilized solution. It is a simple matter of heating the solution to drive off 10x the water to concentrate it. One problem arises because hydrogen peroxide decomposes easily in the presence of light or heat. There are many videos out there about concentrating H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, so I would just like to mention an adaptation I found that helps quell this problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Process &amp; Experimental Set Up&lt;/h4&gt;
H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is subjected to elevated temperatures. Air is passed over the liquid to facilitate evaporation. Care should be taken to minimize foreign particles in the air stream.
&lt;br&gt;My system consists of a candle warmer and a pyrex bowl under an aluminum foil &quot;hat&quot; with a computer fan blowing over it. The foil provides a cover against particles and light (as much as possible anyway).
&lt;h4&gt;Notes&lt;/h4&gt;
The maximum concentration using this method is about 30%. The higher the temperature the faster the decomposition but also the faster you will obtain the end product. If you are willing to wait long enough, you can just let the peroxide sit out. It will slowly (many days or weeks) evaporate. I don't know exactly what the concentration would be since 70% peroxide spontaneously detonates at room temperature. I bet you could use chemical dehydration with silica gel or something similar. That would virtually eliminate particles and decomposition... that will be next.

Watch [this](http://www.youtube.com/embed/xvYeefmbmZI &quot;YouTube&quot;) video for a good demo of the project (not mine).
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/chemistry/2015/08/11/concH2O2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/chemistry/2015/08/11/concH2O2.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Spot Welder</title>
        <description>&lt;div id=&quot;conhead&quot;&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/spotwelder/full.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/projects/spotwelder/full_s.JPG&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; alt=&quot;Spotwelder Image Overview&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;br&gt;Click on the image for the large version.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first got interested in this project because I needed to spot weld titanium cathodes and anodes for the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/chloratecell.html&quot;&gt;Chlorate cell project&lt;/a&gt;. I also use it to make frames for other projects such as the &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/hotplate.html&quot;&gt;$1.49 hot plate&lt;/a&gt;. A quick Google search brought a tutorial from Hack A Day's page: &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://hackaday.com/2009/06/23/how-to-build-your-own-spot-welder/&quot;&gt;Spot Welder&lt;/a&gt;. I started out with a close copy of their spot welder but found it to be unsatisfactory. Probably because I used pre-1982 pennies for the contacts instead of MIG welder tips like they suggested. The wires I used were way too small for the current produced. So I built a second one using steel bolts as the contacts and beefier wiring. It is somewhat better but not the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spot welders join two thin pieces of metal together by resistive heating. The metal is sandwiched between two contacts and a large current (&gt;400 amps) is applied. The contact point between the two metal pieces has a high resistance and heats up to the melting point. The metal flows together and becomes one piece. The current is removed and the is metal allowed to cool. Now you have a spot of welded metal. Spot welders are used industrially to make just about every metal frame on the market from cars to toasters. They give short and precise welding without heating up the whole piece. They are limited to thin metal about nine gauge or smaller and usually aluminum or steel only. Spot welders are usually capacitor bank units instead of the constant source welders made by amateurs. Check out the &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spot_welding&quot;&gt;wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt; on spot welding for more info.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Making of...&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image at the top of the page is the finished welder. I have made lots of good welds with this machine. Overall it took about an hour to make. Most of that time I was fighting with the MOT secondary. It was more of an epic two day battle really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Step 1: Transformer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/spotwelder/transformer.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/projects/spotwelder/transformer_s.JPG&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; alt=&quot;Rewound Transformer&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to do is locate a suitable transformer. Microwave Oven Transformers (MOT) are the best. They are designed for high power applications (&gt;1 KW) and the MOTs are easy to rewind. Not to mention that people throw them out all the time. Often they just have a blown fuse and rarely, if ever, the transformers are blown. If you don't have a microwave to rip apart post an add in your local freecycle or free craigslist. You will undoubtedly get a few hits. Try to find the heaviest transformer you can. Heavier means more power when it comes to transformers. Here is a good &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.instructables.com/id/How-To-Take-Apart-A-Microwave/&quot;&gt;Instructable&lt;/a&gt; about taking apart a microwave. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have a transformer you will have to strip the secondary coil (the fine wire set) in order to rewind it. This takes a combination of strength and skill with a lot of will power. I used a chisel and hammer to shave off the wires on the four points of contact with the laminated core. Alternatively you can just use a cutoff wheel with a dremel. Make sure you wear gloves, a facemask, and goggles when you cut into the secondary. I'm not sure if the epoxy used is toxic but it certainly can't be good for your lungs or eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To rewind the transformer you will need some beefy wires. I used an old set of jumper cables. The smaller the wire you use the faster it will heat up. Certainly don't use anything less than 3 or 4 AWG. Here is a good table for &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.powerstream.com/Wire_Size.htm&quot;&gt;AWG current handling&lt;/a&gt;. If you don't have anything that large you can gang smaller wires together. That's what I did for my first spot welder. The wires would get extremely hot after only a few seconds of use and then I would have to wait for them to cool. Not exactly a fast process. Sorry I don't have pictures of that one. The jumper cables barely heat up even after several welds. Aim to have about three or four turns in your secondary rewinding. This really depends on your wire choice and how big your transformer is. Three to five volts is typically what a spot welder runs at. The cool thing about such a low voltage is that there is very low risk of electrocution. Pretty much the only way to get electrocuted by the arms is if it started raining salt water and then you grabbed both arms. Now that you have a secondary it is time to create the arms and supports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Step 2: Supports and Arms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/spotwelder/supports.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/projects/spotwelder/supports_s.JPG&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; alt=&quot;Supports&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somehow you have to get the power to the metal being welded. You have to be able to maneuver your metal into place and clamp down on it. You also have to carry large currents without heating significantly. Then the arms have to have supports that allow pivot. How do you accomplish all this you ask? I used 3/8&quot; soft copper tubing and sheet metal. It helps to have long, skinny arms like the ones shown. They allow you to make welds in tight places and small spaces. You could use the same wire as the secondary windings for the arms. It would have to be supported somehow. The bottom arm is screwed into the wooden base and electrically insulated from the sheet metal support. The wires from the transformer are just squeezed into the tubing and crimped into place. I used some electrical tape to reduce movement between the two. The support uses a single bolt and two washers as the pivot point.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Step 3: Electrical Control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/spotwelder/switches.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/projects/spotwelder/switches_s.JPG&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; alt=&quot;Power Control Switches&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good spot weld is largely a function of time. Too little time and the metals don't heat enough, too much time and the electrodes degrade and the metal oxidizes producing a poor weld. A regular light switch can be used for timing. Put it in series with the primary winding. They are only designed for about ten amps so you can't put it on the secondary side. I chose to include a second switch as a safety precaution. To operate you must have both switches on.
&lt;br&gt;*Do not forget to core ground your MOT. If you don't the core will kill you if you touch it. All you have to do is connect a grounding wire (usually green) to one of the transformer mounting screws. Doing something so easy to avoid death: probably a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Step 4: Contacts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/spotwelder/contacts.JPG&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/projects/spotwelder/contacts_s.JPG&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; alt=&quot;Welding Contacts&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have some tungsten laying around that would be great. Unfortunately I did not. I used two 1 1/2 inches bolts with a diameter of about 0.25 inch. Definitely not the best choice but it worked. The copper was flattened at the end and a hole drilled through. Two nuts can secure the bolts to the arms. Make sure to sand all the contact points to ensure a good connection. Pretty simple huh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now you have a spot welder. Grab some metal and start welding. &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.robot-welding.com/Welding_parameters.htm&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; page will give you an idea of the spot welding time, cycles, electrode diameter, etc. I typically use three or four cycles at 5 seconds for welding 1.5 mm titanium cathodes. You can do a test weld and then break it. A good weld will rip off a &quot;nugget&quot; of the metal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot;&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;movie&quot; value=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/v/hr-SQwcQj7E?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;allowFullScreen&quot; value=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name=&quot;allowscriptaccess&quot; value=&quot;always&quot;&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/v/hr-SQwcQj7E?version=3&amp;amp;hl=en_US&quot; type=&quot;application/x-shockwave-flash&quot; width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; allowscriptaccess=&quot;always&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2011 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/electronics/2011/12/10/spotwelder.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/electronics/2011/12/10/spotwelder.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>electronics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tesla Coils</title>
        <description>&lt;div id=&quot;conhead&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Ov16ToLt-lM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;DRSSTC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5/15/12&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I built my first DRSSTC in the past few weeks. I had to do a final project for my PHSX 536: Electronic Circuit Design and Measurement class. I didn't choose a wimpy LED flasher circuit or anything like that.... I chose a &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://wiki.4hv.org/index.php/Dual_Resonant_Solid_State_Tesla_Coil&quot;&gt;Dual Resonant Solid State Tesla Coil&lt;/a&gt;. In retrospect, probably not something that should be done in a few weeks. It never officially worked. While taking some voltage measurements one of the 40n60 IGBTs blew up in my face. Scary... but no permanent damage. I wrote a nice &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;/projects/papers/DRSSTC.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; on it however. There might be some things wrong with it. I kinda had to BS a little about the things I didn't understand. Hopefully my teacher doesn't understand either and skips over those parts. You can read it to get a good understanding of the &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://stevehv.4hv.org/drsstc_design.htm&quot;&gt;schematic&lt;/a&gt; I used. Thanks Steve!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;6/5/12&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn't get an internship this summer. :,( On the positive side, now I have nothing to do but everything I want to do. I made a list of things that I want to accomplish this summer. One of them is build an audio modulated DRSSTC with an arc length longer than I am tall (~6'). All my classmates told me to call them when it was finished. Of course I am going to show off!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Secondary&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I have an idea of the arc length that I want. I started browsing around to get an idea of the size I would need to achieve 6'. I again came to Steve's website and his &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://stevehv.4hv.org/DRSSTC2.htm&quot;&gt;DRSSTC-2&lt;/a&gt;. So apparently I am looking at a secondary form size of between 6&quot; and 8&quot;. The local Home Depot sells 4 inch drain pipe (OD=4.215&quot;). This definitely would not suffice. So I settled on the &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.homedepot.com/h_d1/N-5yc1v/R-100321209/h_d2/ProductDisplay?catalogId=10053&amp;langId=-1&quot;&gt;8&quot; cardboard concrete tube&lt;/a&gt;. I have seen multiple websites with various suggestions for aspect ratios. Most stick between 1:3 to 1:5. I will go for 1:4 because its in the middle. The &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://wiki.4hv.org/index.php/Dual_Resonant_Solid_State_Tesla_Coil&quot;&gt;4Hv Wiki&lt;/a&gt; suggests a wire size between 22-28 AWG for an 8&quot; form. I went with 27 AWG because that is what I could find &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://candhsurplus.com/product/wire/page1.htm&quot;&gt;surplus&lt;/a&gt; for a decent price. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Diameter = 7.75&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Length = 43.75&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;27 AWG wire&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;N = 3020 Turns&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;L = 295 mH&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;C = 17 pF&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;f&lt;sub&gt;res&lt;/sub&gt; = 71,190 Hz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;6/10/12&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of you who have been doing these kinds of projects you know what happens when you really get into one. Everything else just kinda falls by the wayside. Unfortunately for you this means that I don't update the site all that often. I do however have a few websites that you should read up on.
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.goodchildengineering.net/tesla-coils&quot;&gt;Goodchild Engineering&lt;/a&gt; - Electrical Engineering student at ASU. Lots of good pics.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://simreal.com/content/TeslaDesignPage1&quot;&gt;Simulated Reality Systems&lt;/a&gt; - Very detailed intro to designing a DRSSTC.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.hilo90mhz.hungrychild.org/tesla/DRSSTC/DRSSTC.html&quot;&gt;Chester's Electronic Labs&lt;/a&gt; - An example of Steve Wards original driver.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;6/15/12&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Controller Board&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally got the controller board done. It is based on Steve Ward's &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://stevehv.4hv.org/new_driver.html&quot;&gt;universal driver 1.3&lt;/a&gt;, but it is modified slightly. The schematic is the same, but I made the PCB more suitable for the &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.instructables.com/id/Cheap-and-Easy-Toner-Transfer-for-PCB-Making/&quot;&gt;Toner Transfer Method&lt;/a&gt; for PCB manufacture. A note on PCBs: don't use Ferric Chloride! It is terrible for the environment. Use &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.instructables.com/id/Stop-using-Ferric-Chloride-etchant!--A-better-etc/&quot;&gt;copper chloride&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/teslacoils/controller.brd&quot;&gt;Controller PCB&lt;/a&gt; - Cadsoft Eagle Board File (Error Fixed 7/11/12)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/teslacoils/controller_transfer.pdf&quot;&gt;Toner Transfer&lt;/a&gt; - PDF file to print on a laser printer&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/projects/teslacoils/controller_parts.txt&quot;&gt;Parts List&lt;/a&gt; - TXT file with a basic parts list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would suggest looking over &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.instructables.com/id/how-to-use-eaglecad/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; instructable for an idea how to use Eagle.
For some reason whenever a board file is saved, the polygon doesn't show up when you reopen it. If you want to edit the board, make sure you use the Ratsnest button to show the GND planes. If you just want to straight copy the board, you can use the transfer page. It is just a pdf file with two copies of the top and bottom of the board to be used in the Toner Transfer Method. The parts list is the same (nearly) as Steve Ward's. Some of the parts are obsolete so you might have to substitute. I will try and post a copy of the order I placed with Mouser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Simulations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://wiki.4hv.org/index.php/ScanTesla&quot;&gt;Scan Tesla&lt;/a&gt; was developed by Terry Fritz in order to simply simulate a tesla coil (both solid state and original) using lumped circuit elements. Basically you just input the possible dimensions of your coil (secondary and primary inductance, tank capacitance, etc.) and Scan Tesla runs through each possibility and spits out the best one. Pretty neat software I must say. So anyway, &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/teslacoils/input.txt&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is the input text file and &lt;a href=&quot;/projects/teslacoils/output.txt&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is the output I get. I ended up winding 43.75&quot; before running out of space. That works out to be about 3000 turns of wire. Quite a bit higher than you usually see. Scan tesla suggested that the benefits of a higher inductance outweighed the increase in resistance. I guess we will see... I measured the resistance of the wire using a standard digital multimeter. The &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://hamwaves.com/antennas/inductance.html&quot;&gt;inductance calculator&lt;/a&gt; I used suggested that my resistance should be around 1300 ohms. It was 289 ohms. Something is wrong here. Maybe the inductance calculator includes some reactance from the inductor as well? They do ask for the design frequency which would suggest they did. I am hoping that 289 ohms is right. My output drops significantly if the secondary resistance is 1300 ohms, obviously. The expected resistance for 27 AWG wire is about 51 ohms per thousand feet. That gives about 315 ohms resistance total. Much closer to what I measured. Skin depth is greater than the conductor diameter (below 130 KHz anyway).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might try and modify Scan Tesla to include some practical design considerations. If you want to find the ideal number of turns in your coil you have to run separate simulations because secondary resistance and inductance are not linked. The program would just use the lowest resistance and highest inductance. Hardly a real world situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;IGBTs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am using the &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://ixdev.ixys.com/DataSheet/99177.pdf&quot;&gt;IXYS 60N60C2D1&lt;/a&gt; brick IGBT. A lot of people say that it is underpowered for DRSSTC work, but it was cheap and still available on Mouser. It isn't that hard to adapt a system to a different IGBT if I want to upgrade later. I ran into &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.microsemi.com/en/sites/default/files/micnotes/APT0201.pdf&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; article on IGBTs. It is a great read and very helpful. I would suggest at least browsing through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Gate Driver Transformers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://wiki.4hv.org/index.php/Gate_drive_transformer&quot;&gt;HvWiki&lt;/a&gt; on GDTs is very helpful. Check thedatastream.4hv.org link at the bottom of that page for some more info on GDTs. So now that I have an IGBT, I can start calculations on the GDT. I choose to use B64290L618X38 toroidal ferrites from Epcos. Probably should buy the next size up to increase the cross sectional surface area, but they work for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Drive Voltage = 12V&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Frequency = 67.7 KHz&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A&lt;sub&gt;L&lt;/sub&gt; = 10,700 nH/N&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;XSA = 51.26 mm&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that I need more than 8.3 turns to avoid saturation. With 10 turns... The inductance is 1.07 mH. The magnitizing current (rms) is 48 mA. The gate current is 13 mA. The total current a driver must supply is 61 mA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6/20/12&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finished ordering the components for the controller board from mouser. Click &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.mouser.com/ProjectManager/ProjectDetail.aspx?AccessID=ef87f8155c&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to access the order. I might have ordered some extra things or forgot something, but that should give you a good idea what to purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ordered some &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.cde.com/catalogs/942C.pdf&quot;&gt;942C20P15K-F&lt;/a&gt; capacitors today. I was looking at $8.35 a piece from mouser. Thankfully, I found a better place: &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.onlinecomponents.com/cornell-dubilier_942c20p15k-f.html?p=10932642&quot;&gt;Online Components&lt;/a&gt;. Woohoo for $3.75 each. Plus the minimum order is 1. I feel much better now. I guess we will see if they are a good supplier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan on using 4 in series and 5 in parallel for a total of 188nF at 6000 VDC. I will add some 940C20s that I bought earlier by mistake to increase the capacitance to 263nF. Hopefully they won't feel ashamed by their bigger cousins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;7/11/12&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't done much these past couple of weeks. I made the primary coil supports. Made the MMC bank. Finished the control board. I just have the last bit of contruction to do. Then it will be time for first light! I still have to test the control board. It is a new design afterall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A note on the controller board: the 9 Volt power line was bridged to the two outputs of the UCC27423. I noticed this only after I had completed my board. I just sanded off the connection. I fixed the problem on the Eagle board file, but not the transfer. I will get to that in a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;7/27/12&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It Works!!!! I got first light on the massive coil. Three feet at least. I didn't have time to measure before death however. It took a bit of fiddling and rigging to get it to work though. I figured out that the opto-isolator used by Steve Ward inverted the interrupter signal, so there was an extra run through the 74HC14 hex-inverting trigger. Good thing my over current detector wasn't working correctly. It somehow blocked the signal no matter what. I will have to take a look at that. It might have something to do with the fact that the 74HC74 flip-flop that Steve used being active high, while mine (the TI version) was active low. I fixed the extra inverter on the .brd file above by passing the interrupter through an extra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I tried to use a microcontroller to audio-modulate the interrupter. Catastrophic failure resulted... I haven't had time to look at it though. I had it disabled at the time of failure obviously. So now the question: I designed the system for bolt-in replacement of the IGBTs. I can spend the $40 to replace the two blown ones, or I can try to upgrade. CM300s seem to be a popular choice, but they require more complicated drivers. &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://thedatastream.4hv.org/inazuma_mk1_drsstc.htm&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; guy tried to use TO-247 IGBTs which are much cheaper. Three or four dollars a piece. The mounting is harder though. I think I will attempt to parallel two IGBTs each in a full-bridge for a total of eight. More on this to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;10/14/12&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I finally got around to ordering replacement 60n60s. I got some TO-247s as well (FGH40N60SMD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;07/24/13&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I have been tasked with igniting the bonfire at a local caving meeting. A couple years ago I was assigned the same task and I used a flame thrower to accomplish said task. Obviously I have to do better this year. So I was thinking... why not use a tesla coil?? I could even improve upon my last design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking about it over the last couple weeks and I have decided on a DRSSTC magnifier system based on Tesla's original patents. If you haven't already, read over Tesla's Colorado Springs notes. It helped a lot. So I am thinking a three coil system would be best. A tightly coupled primary and secondary with a detacted free resonator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Thought Experiment&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine a swing. Any swing will go. Imagine that you have a fiend on that swing who like to go really high. If you push the swing once, it develops a certain natural rythmic frequency. After a couple swings it slows down and eventually comes to a hault. In order to get the largest swing it is beneficial to make the intial push very fast and very hard thus allowing for the greatest impart of energy. Alternately you could impart the same energy over several periods of oscillation by striking the swing at the same frequency as the natural one. A short push (and detachment) at the crest of each swing is sufficient. Now imagine that the only way for you to push this swing is with a spring that is permanently attached to the swing and you. The best way to achieve height for your friend on the swing is to match the springs size and strength to that of the swing. That way, you can continue to provide small pushes at the crest of the oscillation. A spring that isn't matched to the same frequency will only hurt the height. &lt;br /&gt; If you haven't figured it out already the swing system is a tesla coil. The swing, spring, and you are the free resonator, secondary, and primary, respectively. A few changes have to be made however. In a Tesla magnifier the primary is tightly coupled to the secondary to get the fastest energy transfer. It is also not resonant which means instead of a spring to push and pull the swing, you just have a pole. &lt;br /&gt;I would say that the best system is one that grabs the swing with a perfect grip at any point (most likely crossing zero deflection) and pushes the swing in the direction of motion. After the maximum energy has been transferred, the grip is let go. Now... how to do this in a tesla coil? Well you certainly need a system with the same resonating frequency in both the primary tank circuit and secondary/free coil circuit. That was Tesla's first discovery. You also need a mechanism for aligning the frequencies and for gripping/letting go of the coil. Most coils use loose coupling between the primary and secondary to achive this. But that means relatively small amounts of energy are transferred per cycle. Its like using a continuous stream of water from a hose to push your swing. If the stream is also varying in strength according to its resonance (that matches the swing's) it won't disconnect persay, but it will slow down or stop when pushing in the opposite direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;07/25/13 Designing a Tesla Coil&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been working on this for a few days now: trying to find formulas that define the best configuration of a tesla coil. While reading through the Colorado Springs Notes I saw a remark made by Tesla, &quot;Now the secondary, to be at best, should work with all jars [capacitors] available and the regulating coil should be all cut out in the primary. This is namely the condition corresponding to the full output and the highest economy.&quot; Tesla had to use an additional inductor in the tank circuit to tune the coil since he used a static, unadjustable primary. So anyway... I will keep a list here of basic design principles that may or may not be correct or up to date as I add to it:
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Higher inductance to resistance ratio results in a better performing coil. ie. L/R is proportional to Q. &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Q_factor#RLC_circuits&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reduce parasitic capacitance in all coils. &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parasitic_capacitance&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Total length of any resonating circuit must be 1/4 of the wavelength of the standing wave in the material.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Use the largest capacitance your power supply can handle.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The ratio of inductances between primary and secondary (free resonator) determine the maximum voltage gain.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The coil is meant to resonate: coupling is key.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
And now some explanations on each point...
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Obviously you should reduce resistance and increase inductance here. The problem is that they are inversely related. The more turns of wire you put on a certain form (increasing L), the greater the resistance due to added length. Tesla initially tried to cool the coils below room temperature (he even has a patent for cooling with liquid air) to decrease resistance. His later work does not use this method however. I suppose that it could be the increase in parasitic capacitance due to a higher permitivity surrounding the coil. Immersing the coil in a liquid increases the capacitance between the wires and adds to the overall impedance. I'm sure there is a balance between the two. Just adding dry ice to a coil can decrease the resistance by 40% or more. With a tube type primary coil it might be possible to cool by pumping a cooling fluid through. Something like dry ice in acetone as a cheap alternative to liquid N2. I was thinking of making the coil as a standalone form (sealed with some protectant) and just stuffing the center with dry ice during runs. I can't find anything on the loss tangent of solid CO2 so I guess I will just have to experiment.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Parasitic capacitance is as bad as it sounds. Between each coil on a form there exists a voltage difference. And with any voltage difference there comes a capacitance. It is on the order of 1 pF or less, but it is there none the less. Each little inductor capacitor circuit has its own resonant frequency which is much higher that that of the whole coil. The distributed capacitance has the effect of many little spring-mass systems on our swing example. They must be charged and discharged with each cycle adding to the total loss and reduces energy transfer to the system. I guess you could try to design a system where the resonant frequency of the parasite caps and inductors is an overtone of the whole system... One way of accomplishing reducing loss is to increase the spacing between wires. The greater the distance the lower the capacitance. This is fine for the free resonator, but the secondary needs to be tighly coupled to the primary and thus needs tighly spaced wires. Additionally the greater the spacing, the lower the inductance for a certain height so you run into physical constraints. &lt;br /&gt;Another possibility is to limit the dielectric covering wires. A higher &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.rfcafe.com/references/electrical/dielectric-constants-strengths.htm&quot;&gt;permitivity&lt;/a&gt; will results in larger capacitance as well. Teflon (PTFE), single build magnet wire is probably the best you can get right now in terms of low permitivity (~2) and loss (0.0003). But that comes at a (very large) price. Regular magnet wire is usually polyurethane (3.5 and 0.008). The coating is very thin so there isn't that much to worry about. Obviously whatever form you use for your coil will also benefit from a low permitivity and low loss. PVC is not too bad for permitivity but the loss is horrible (~3 and 0.02). Its even worse because PVC absorbs moisture (&gt;55 and &gt;0.04). Obviously vaccum would be the best (1 and 0) but who can afford that large a vaccum chamber...? Alternatively you can just use air, but it has a very low breakdown voltage. The voltage difference between wires might be enough to arc over and destroy the coil. Tesla also suggested in his magnifier patent to keep the wire spacing at a minimum to ensure the coil acted as a single conductor of the diameter of the coil form to reduce leakage to the atmosphere. Some testing or simulation is needed to find the best configuration here. Check out &lt;a target=&quot;new_window&quot; href=&quot;http://www.g3ynh.info/zdocs/magnetics/appendix/self_res/self-res.pdf&quot;&gt;this paper (pdf)&lt;/a&gt; for a good discussion on solenoid inductance and self capacitance. In short, parasitic capacitance is extremely hard to calculate. I used the doubly-asymptotic, empirically corrected (DAE) formula for self capacitance.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;This is kinda debated among the community and I don't really understand why. Basically the coil develops a standing electrical wave in operation. Ensuring the coil's length is close to 1/4 the wavelength of EM radiation in your conductor of choice keeps the first anti-node (and thus the highest potential) near the top. I rarely see the 1/4 wave idea talked about except in highly studied (normally academic based) tesla designs. Tesla reiterated the point almost every time he designed a coil so I'm going to stick with that idea.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The whole point of a coil is the get the largest amount of energy into the secondary (and free resonator) and transform that energy into the largest electrical field possible. This starts with the tank circuit storing the largest amount of power. Obviously you are limited by the amount of power by your supply. For example, if you have a variac that can only take 10 Amps, that would be your limit. You should choose the largest cap that 10 Amps can charge at whatever voltage and design from there. With a larger capacitor, comes a smaller inductor for the same frequency however. A smaller inductor will most likely have a smaller coupling thus limiting the transfer of energy per cycle. You give some, you take some... electrical power that is.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;As with any transformer, the ratio of inductances determines the voltage gain. There is certainly more at work here but for simplicity's sake (and my own ignorance) I won't go into detail. But just know that you are aiming for the highest inductance possible in the secondary and free resonator while still maintaining a strong transfer of energy. Also, I saw on some website that I can't remember that it is advisable to keep the free resonator above 3x the inductance of the secondary. The point was illustrated as a bell being struck by a clapper. A 5 lb bell would be ill suited by a 1 ton clapper. Anything more than some inductance smaller than the free resonator would be a waste.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Not only do you want a large transfer of energy but you also need to let the coil resonate to get the largest voltage. Ideally you would strike (input energy then disconnect) the free resonator with some set of energy and let it ring by itself. Unfortunately this is kinda impossible due to physical constraints. The only way to do it is to transfer energy slowly over several oscillations with a very loose coupling. The transfer goes both ways in this kind of system though. Energy will be taken out of the resonator and dumped back in the primary. Every time the energy oscillated back to the starting position (magnetic energy in the inductor), energy is lost to the primary again. A loose coupling between the systems helps eliminate this. It seems to me that the worst problem with the whole tesla coil design is the limit imposed by the coupling. The ultimate limitation is in the transfer of energy back to the primary tank on each cycle, not the resistance or other means of dissipation of the secondary. Some simulation is necessary here. &lt;br /&gt;Tesla originally used a flat pancake secondary to combat this. The outermost coil was grounded and the innermost coil was the output. The primary encircled the secondary. That way you could get a very good transfer of energy to the outermost coils and the inner part would resonate freely (sort of). Tesla later moved on to the three coil magnifier system as a way to further reduce the coupling problem. A detached free resonator was electrically connected to an unresonating secondary of high coupling to the primary. Energy could be transferred to the secondary effectively over very few cycles and the free coil could resonate without magnetically transferring energy back to the primary. It seems to me that you still have transfer through the secondary to the primary but who knows. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2003 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/electronics/2003/05/01/teslacoils.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/electronics/2003/05/01/teslacoils.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>electronics</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
